A Finding Aid to the Jorge Tacla Papers, 1966-2019, bulk 1980-2009, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Jorge Tacla papers
1966-2019
bulk 1980-2009
Archives of American Art
Tacla, Jorge, 1958-
AAA.tacljorg
Archival Resource Key
5.05 Linear feet
The papers of Chilean born painter Jorge Tacla measure 5.05 linear feet and date from 1966-2019. Included are biographical material; letters from friends and other artists; project and exhibition files; photographs consisting of snaphots of Tacla, friends, and paintings; eleven illustrated journals; and printed material. The papers document Tacla's creative process and his relationships with other artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1980-circa 1992 (0.2 linear feet, Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1981-2013 (0.7 linear feet, Box 1, 7)
Series 3: Exhibition Files, 1991-2009 (0.1 linear feet, Box 1)
Series 4: Legal Records, 1996 (0.3 linear feet, Box 1-2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1980-2019 (2.3 linear feet, Box 2-3, 7-10)
Series 6: Artwork, 1986-2019 (0.9 linear feet, Box 3, 5-6, 10)
Series 7: Photographic Material, 1981-2018 (0.55 linear feet, Box 3-4)
Biographical / Historical
Jorge Tacla (1958-) is a Chilean born painter who lives in and primarily works in New York, New York.
Tacla attended the Escuela de Bellas Artes, Universidad de Chile and moved to New York in 1981. Throughout his career, Tacla has been awarded numerous grants and fellowships including the John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation Fellowship in 1988. His paintings often present half-imaginary landscapes, such as a disintegrating urban site or a pristine desert. Tacla's work has been included in numerous group and solo exhibitions at galleries and museums around the world.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing born-digital records or audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated in 2019 by Jorge Tacla.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Chilean born painter Jorge Tacla measure 5.05 linear feet and date from 1966-2019. Included are biographical material; letters from friends and other artists; project and exhibition files; photographs consisting of snaphots of Tacla, friends, and paintings; eleven illustrated journals; and printed material. The papers document Tacla's creative process and his relationships with other artists.
This collection documents source material for Tacla's paintings, the creative process through which he makes paintings, his career as an artist working in New York and Chile, and his friendships with other artists. Materials include immigration papers; resumes; an artist bio; an oral history interview transcript; personal and professional correspondence; draft essays; sketches; drawings; sketchbooks; exhibition announcements, catalogs, posters, checklists, and press packets; clippings related to major world events and reviews of Tacla's work; and photographs of Tacla with other artists and colleagues, friends and family, installations, his studios in New York and Chile, and his work.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Drawings; Sketchbooks; Interviews; Díaz, Gonzalo, 1947-; Jaar, Alfredo
- Biographical Material, circa 1980-circa1992; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1-5
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical material provides a snapshot of Tacla's career through immigration papers, his artist bio, an oral history interview transcript, and resumes. Also included are an ex-ray of Tacla's head, two sonograms, correspondence, and a photocopy of his ID card.
  - Artist Bios, X-ray, Sonograms, Sketches, 1987-circa 1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Drafts, Universidad de Chile, circa 1980-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Immigration Documentation, circa 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Transcript of Oral History Interview with Jorge Tacla, 1987-1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1981-2013; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.7 Linear feet Box 1, 7
  Correspondence, mainly in Spanish, include personal and professional letters with friends and fellow artists, and letters from curators and dealers about exhibitions. Many of the letters are illustrated and highlight Tacla's close friendships with other artists in New York and Chile. Artists of note include Alfredo Jaar, Gonzalo Diaz, and Nuri Gonzales.
  - Personal, 1981-1996, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Personal, 1981-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Personal, 1981-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Personal, 1981-1993, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Personal, 1981-1993, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Personal, 1981-1994, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Personal, 1981-1996, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal, 1982-1994, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Professional, No Freedom No Culture Conference, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Professional, Bronx Housing Court, 1991-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Professional, 1981-1997, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Professional, 1982-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Professional, 1981-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Professional, 1992-circa 2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Professional, 1998, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Personal, 1983-1986, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Exhibition Files, 1991-2009; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.1 Linear feet Box 1
  Exhibition files document Tacla's work with curators through correspondence, draft essays, posters, sketches, checklists, floor plans, and press packets including a project with the High Museum of art in the early 1990s. Exhibitions of note include "Jorge Tacla Senal de Abandono" (2000), "Kill the Song" (2008), and "Propuesta Conceptual: Obra Permanente Museo de la Memoria" (2009).
  - High Museum of Art, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Jorge Tacla: Senal de Abandono (2000), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Kill the Song (2008), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Propuesta Conceptual: Obra Permanente Museo de la Memoria (2009), Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Legal Records, 1966; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Legal records include a lengthy deposition related to a lawsuit with the landlord of Tacla's studio in which Tacla describes in detail his artistic process.
  - Deposition, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Deposition, 1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
- Printed Material, 1980-2019; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 2.3 Linear feet Box 2-3, 7-10
  Printed materials highlight Tacla's career as a painter through exhibition announcements and catalogs, and newspaper and magazine clippings of reviews or articles about his work. The clippings also include major events that inspired Tacla's artistic process, including the 2001 attacks on the World Trade Center, the 2008 election of Barak Obama, the death of Osama Bin Laden in 2011, the 2008 Chaiten volcano eruption in southern Chile, and the Bali bombings of nightclubs and bars in 2002.
  - Articles, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes and Post Cards, circa 1983-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1985-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 2003-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, Annotated, 2011-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1983-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1988-1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1995-2019, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1986-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1991-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1993; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1993-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1996-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1999-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 2008-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Clippings, 1980-2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1982-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1985-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1984-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1984-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1985, 2005-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 1986- 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1984-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1986-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1988-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Clippings, 1988-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1988-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Clippings, 1989-2017; Archival Resource Key (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
  - Clippings, 2002-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1994-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - Exhibition and Event Posters, 1985, 2010, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Artwork, 1986-2018; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.9 Linear feet Box 3, 5-6, 10
  Artwork demonstrates preliminary work for Tacla's paintings from the 1980s and 1990s to 2018 through eleven notebooks containing drawings, paintings, and writings; two of Tacla's zines; and select drawings. One of the sketchbooks documents a trip Tacla took to Amsterdam in 1986.
  - Drawings, 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Loose Drawings, 1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Selected Drawings from "Identitades Ocultas" Notebook, 2011-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Selection of Drawings from "Roma" Notebook, 2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Selected Drawings, Pencil on Paper, 2012; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbooks, Amsterdam Travels, 1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbooks, 1986-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbooks, 1989-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Sketchbooks, 1989-1992; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbook, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Sketchbooks, 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbooks, 1989-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbooks, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Zines, 1984, 2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Photographic Material, 1981-2018; Series 7; Archival Resource Key; 0.55 Linear feet Box 3-4
  Photographic material highlights Tacla's career and his relationships with artists, curators, and dealers. Materials include color and black and white photographs, and slides depicting installations, Tacla's paintings and studios in New York and Chile, and personal snapshots of Tacla with friends, family, and colleagues.
  - Black and White Photos of Artwork, 1982-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Color Photos of Studio in New York 32nd Street and Camila, 1998-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Low Resolution Phone Images of Studio, Installations, and Friends, 2013-2018; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Photos of Artwork, Bronx Housing Court, 1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Photos of Tacla, Studio, and Nature, 1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Photos of Friends and Family, 1980-2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photos of Friends and Family and Studio, 2002-2007; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photos of Friends and Family and Studio in Chile, 1987-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Photos of Friends and Family, Studio, and Exhibitions, 1982-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Photos of Guggenheim Project in Atacama Desert, 1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Photos of Jorge Tacla, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photos of Jorge Tacla and Studio, 1981-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Photos of Studios, 2000-2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photos of Studio and Homes in New York City, 1982-2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Slides, Artwork, 1981-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 4, Folder 3-4)